PROFESSOR: Well, I hope you
appreciate that we have
inducted you into some real
magic, the magic of building
languages, really building
new languages.
What have we looked at?
We've looked at an Escher
picture language: this
language invented by
Peter Henderson.
We looked at digital
logic language.
Let's see.
We've looked at the
query language.
And the thing you should realize
is, even though these
were toy examples, they really
are the kernels of really
useful things.
So, for instance, the Escher
picture language was taken by
Henry Wu, who's a student at
MIT, and developed into a real
language for laying out PC
boards based just on extending
those structures.
And the digital logic language,
Jerry mentioned when
he showed it to you, was really
extended to be used as
the basis for a simulator
that was used to
design a real computer.
And the query language,
of course, is kind
of the germ of prologue.
So we built all of these
languages, they're
all based on LISP.
A lot of people ask what
particular problems is LISP
good for solving for?
The answer is LISP is not good
for solving any particular
problems. What LISP is good for
is constructing within it
the right language to solve
the problems you want to
solve, and that's how you
should think about it.
So all of these languages
were based on LISP.
Now, what's LISP based on?
Where's that come from?
Well, we looked at that too.
We looked at the meta-circular
evaluator and said well, LISP
is based on LISP.
And when we start looking at
that, we've got to do some
real magic, right?
So what does that mean, right?
Why operators, and fixed points,
and the idea that what
this means is that LISP is
somehow the fixed-point
equation for this funny set of
things which are defined in
terms of themselves.
Now, it's real magic.
Well, today, for a final piece
of magic, we're going to make
all the magic go away.
We already know how
to do that.
The idea is, we're going to
take the register machine
architecture and show
how to implement
LISP on terms of that.
And, remember, the idea of the
register machine is that
there's a fixed and finite
part of the machine.
There's a finite-state
controller, which does some
particular thing with a
particular amount of hardware.
There are particular data
paths: the operation the
machine does.
And then, in order to implement
recursion and
sustain the illusion of
infinity, there's some large
amount of memory, which
is the stack.
So, if we implement LISP in
terms of a register machine,
then everything ought to
become, at this point,
completely concrete.
All the magic should go away.
And, by the end of this talk,
I want you get the feeling
that, as opposed to this very
mysterious meta-circular
evaluator, that a LISP evaluator
really is something
that's concrete enough that
you can hold in the
palm of your hand.
You should be able to
imagine holding a
LISP interpreter there.
All right, how are we
going to do this?
We already have all
the ingredients.
See, what you learned last time
from Jerry is how to take
any particular couple of LISP
procedures and hand-translate
them into something that runs
on a register machine.
So, to implement all of LISP on
a register machine, all we
have to do is take the
particular procedures that are
the meta-circular evaluator and
hand-translate them for a
register machine.
And that does all
of LISP, right?
So, in principle, we already
know how to do this.
And, indeed, it's going to be
no different, in kind, from
translating, say, recursive
factorial
or recursive Fibonacci.
It's just bigger and
there's more of it.
So it'd just be more details,
but nothing really
conceptually new.
All right, also, when we've done
that, and the thing is
completely explicit, and we see
how to implement LISP in
terms of the actual sequential
register operations, that's
going to be our final most
explicit model of
LISP in this course.
And, remember, that's
a progression
through this course.
We started out with
substitution, which is sort of
like algebra.
And then we went to the
environment model, which
talked about the actual
frames and how
they got linked together.
And then we made that
more concrete in the
meta-circular evaluator.
There are things the
meta-circular evaluator
doesn't tell us.
You should realize that.
For instance, it left unanswered
the question of how
a procedure, like recursive
factorial here , somehow takes
space that grows.
On the other hand, a procedure
which also looks syntactically
recursive, called fact-iter,
somehow doesn't take space.
We justify that it doesn't need
to take space by showing
the substitution model.
But we didn't really say how
it happens that the machine
manages to do that, that that
has to do with the details of
how arguments are passed
to procedures.
And that's the thing we didn't
see in the meta-circular
evaluator precisely because the
way arguments got passed
to procedures in this LISP
depended on the way arguments
got passed to procedures
in this LISP.
But, now, that's going to become
extremely explicit.
OK.
Well, before going on to the
evaluator, let me just give
you a sense of what a whole LISP
system looks like so you
can see the parts we're going
to talk about and the parts
we're not going to talk about.
Let's see, over here is a happy
LISP user, and the LISP
user is talking to something
called the reader.
The reader's job in life is to
take characters from the user
and turn them into data
structures in something called
a list structure memory.
All right, so the reader is
going to take symbols,
parentheses, and A's and B's,
and ones and threes that you
type in, and turn these into
actual list structure: pairs,
and pointers, and things.
And so, by the time evaluator
is going, there are no
characters in the world.
And, of course, in more modern
list systems, there's sort of
a big morass here that might sit
between the user and the
reader: Windows systems, and top
levels, and mice, and all
kinds of things.
But conceptually, characters
are coming in.
All right, the reader transforms
these into pointers
to stuff in this memory,
and that's what the
evaluator sees, OK?
The evaluator has a
bunch of helpers.
It has all possible primitive
operators you might want.
So there's a completely separate
box, a floating point
unit, or all sorts of
things, which do
the primitive operators.
And, if you want more special
primitives, you build more
primitive operators,
but they're
separate from the evaluator.
The evaluator finally gets an
answer and communicates that
to the printer.
And now, the printer's job in
life is to take this list
structure coming from the
evaluator, and turn it back
into characters, and communicate
them to the user
through whatever interface
there is.
OK.
Well, today, what we're
going to talk
about is this evaluator.
The primitive operators have
nothing particular to do with
LISP, they're however you like
to implement primitive
operations.
The reader and printer are
actually complicated, but
we're not going to
talk about them.
They sort of have to do with
details of how you might build
up list structure
from characters.
So that is a long story,
but we're not going
to talk about it.
The list structure memory, we'll
talk about next time.
So, pretty much, except for
the details of reading and
printing, the only mystery
that's going to be left after
you see the evaluator is how
you build list structure on
conventional memories.
But we'll worry about
that next time too.
OK.
Well, let's start talking
about the evaluator.
The one that we're going to show
you, of course, is not, I
think, nothing special
about it.
It's just a particular register
machine that runs LISP.
And it has seven registers,
and here
are the seven registers.
There's a register, called EXP,
and its job is to hold
the expression to
be evaluated.
And by that, I mean it's going
to hold a pointer to someplace
in list structure memory
that holds the
expression to be evaluated.
There's a register, called
ENV, which holds the
environment in which this
expression is to be evaluated.
And, again, I made a pointer.
The environment is some
data structure.
There's a register, called
FUN, which will hold the
procedure to be applied when you
go to apply a procedure.
A register, called ARGL,
which wants the list
of evaluated arguments.
What you can start seeing
here is the basic
structure of the evaluator.
Remember how evaluators work.
There's a piece that takes
expressions and environments,
and there's a piece that
takes functions, or
procedures and arguments.
And going back and forth
around here is
the eval/apply loop.
So those are the basic pieces
of the eval and apply.
Then there's some other things,
there's continue.
You just saw before how the
continue register is used to
implement recursion and
stack discipline.
There's a register that's going
to hold the result of
some evaluation.
And then, besides that,
there's one temporary
register, called UNEV, which
typically, in the evaluator,
is going to be used to hold
temporary pieces of the
expression you're working on,
which you haven't gotten
around to evaluate yet, right?
So there's my machine: a
seven-register machine.
And, of course, you might want
to make a machine with a lot
more registers to get better
performance, but this is just
a tiny, minimal one.
Well, how about the
data paths?
This machine has a lot of
special operations for LISP.
So, here are some typical
data paths.
A typical one might be, oh,
assign to the VAL register the
contents of the EXP register.
In terms of those diagrams you
saw, that's a little button on
some arrow.
Here's a more complicated one.
It says branch, if the thing in
the expression register is
a conditional to some label
here, called the
ev-conditional.
And you can imagine this
implemented in a lot of
different ways.
You might imagine this
conditional test as a special
purpose sub-routine, and
conditional might be
represented as some data
abstraction that you don't
care about at this
level of detail.
So that might be done
as a sub-routine.
This might be a machine with
hardware-types, and
conditional might be testing
some bits for
a particular code.
There are all sorts of ways
that's beneath the level of
abstraction we're looking at.
Another kind of operation, and
there are a lot of different
operations assigned to
EXP, the first clause
of what's in EXP.
This might be part of processing
a conditional.
And, again, first clause is some
selector whose details we
don't care about.
And you can, again, imagine that
as a sub-routine which'll
do some list operations, or
you can imagine that as
something that's built directly
into hardware.
The reason I keep saying you can
imagine it built directly
into hardware is even though
there are a lot of operations,
there are still a fixed
number of them.
I forget how many, maybe 150.
So, it's plausible to think
of building these
directly into hardware.
Here's a more complicated one.
You can see this has to
do with looking up
the values of variables.
It says assign to the VAL
register the result of looking
up the variable value of some
particular expression, which,
in this case, is supposed
to be a variable in some
environment.
And this'll be some operation
that searches through the
environment structure, however
it is represented, and goes
and looks up that variable.
And, again, that's below the
level of detail that we're
thinking about.
This has to do with the details
of the data structures
for representing environments.
But, anyway, there is this fixed
and finite number of
operations in the register
machine.
Well, what's its overall
structure?
Those are some typical
operations.
Remember what we have to
do, we have to take the
meta-circular evaluator--
and here's a piece of the
meta-circular evaluator.
This is the one using abstract
syntax that's in the book.
It's a little bit different
from the one
that Jerry shows you.
And the main thing to remember
about the evaluator is that
it's doing some sort of case
analysis on the kinds of
expressions: so if it's either
self-evaluated, or quoted, or
whatever else.
And then, in the general case
where the expression it's
looking at is an application,
there's some tricky
recursions going on.
First of all, eval has to call
itself both to evaluate the
operator and to evaluate
all the operands.
So there's this sort of red
recursion of values walking
down the tree that's really
the easy recursion.
That's just a val walking down
this tree of expressions.
Then, in the evaluator, there's
a hard recursion.
There's the red to green.
Eval calls apply.
That's the case where evaluating
a procedure or
argument reduces to applying
the procedure
to the list of arguments.
And then, apply comes
over here.
Apply takes a procedure and
arguments and, in the general
case where there's a compound
procedure, apply goes around
and green calls red.
Apply comes around and
calls eval again.
Eval's the body of the procedure
in the result of
extending the environment with
the parameters of the
procedure by binding
the arguments.
Except in the primitive case,
where it just calls something
else primitive-apply, which
is not really the
business of the evaluator.
So this sort of red to green,
to red to green, that's the
eval/apply loop, and that's the
thing that we're going to
want to see in the evaluator.
All right.
Well, it won't surprise you at
all that the two big pieces of
this evaluator correspond
to eval and apply.
There's a piece called
eval-dispatch, and a piece
called apply-dispatch.
And, before we get into the
details of the code, the way
to understand this is to think,
again, in terms of
these pieces of the evaluator
having contracts with the rest
of the world.
What do they do from the outside
before getting into
the grungy details?
Well, the contract for
eval-dispatch--
remember, it corresponds
to eval.
It's got to evaluate an
expression in an environment.
So, in particular, what this
one is going to do,
eval-dispatch will assume that,
when you call it, that
the expression you
want to evaluate
is in the EXP register.
The environment in which you
want the evaluation to take
place is in the ENV register.
And continue tells you the place
where the machine should
go next when the evaluation
is done.
Eval-dispatch's contract is that
it'll actually perform
that evaluation, and, at the end
of which, it'll end up at
the place specified
by continue.
The result of the evaluation
will be in the VAL register.
And it just warns you, it makes
no promises about what
happens to the registers.
All other registers might
be destroyed.
So, there's one piece, OK?
Together, the pieces,
apply-dispatch that
corresponds to apply, it's got
to apply a procedure to some
arguments, so it assumes that
this register, ARGL, contains
a list of the evaluated
arguments.
FUN contains the procedure.
Those correspond to the
arguments to the apply
procedure in the meta-circular
evaluator.
And apply, in this particular
evaluator, we're going to use
a discipline which says the
place the machine should go to
next when apply is done is, at
the moment apply-dispatch is
called at the top of the stack,
that's just discipline
for the way this particular
machine's organized.
And now apply's contract
is given all that.
It'll perform the application.
The result of that application
will end up in VAL.
The stack will be popped.
And, again, the contents of all
the other registers may be
destroyed, all right?
So that's the basic organization
of this machine.
Let's break for a little bit
and see if there are any
questions, and then we'll
do a real example.
Well, let's take the register
machine now, and actually step
through, and really, in real
detail, so you see completely
concrete how some expressions
are evaluated, all right?
So, let's start with a very
simple expression.
Let's evaluate the
expression 1.
And we need an environment, so
let's imagine that somewhere
there's an environment,
we'll call it E,0.
And just, since we'll use these
later, we obviously
don't really need anything
to evaluate 1.
But, just for reference later,
let's assume that E,0 has in
it an X that's bound to 3 and
a Y that's bound to 4, OK?
And now what we're going to do
is we're going to evaluate 1
in this environment, and so the
ENV register has a pointer
to this environment,
E,0, all right?
So let's watch that thing go.
What I'm going to do is
step through the code.
And, let's see, I'll
be the controller.
And now what I need, since this
gets rather complicated,
is a very little
execution unit.
So here's the execution
unit, OK?
OK.
All right, now we're
going to start.
We're going to start
the machine at
eval-dispatch, right?
That's the beginning of this.
Eval-dispatch is going to look
at the expression in dispatch,
just like eval where we look
at the very first thing.
We branch on whether or
not this expression is
self-evaluating.
Self-evaluating is some
abstraction we
put into the machine--
it's going to be true
for numbers--
to a place called ev-self-eval,
right?
So me, being the controller,
looks at ev-self-eval, so
we'll go over to there.
Ev-self-eval says fine, assign
to val whatever is in the
expression unit, OK?
And I have a bug because what I
didn't do when I initialized
this machine is also say what's
supposed to happen when
it's done, so I should have
started out the machine with
done being in the continue
register, OK?
So we assign to VAL.
And now go to fetch
of continue, and
now change--
OK.
OK, let's try something
harder.
Let's reset the machine here,
and we'll put in the
expression register, X, OK?
Start again at eval-dispatch.
Check, is it self-evaluating?
No.
Is it a variable?
Yes.
We go off to ev-variable.
It says assign to VAL, look up
the variable value in the
expression register, OK?
Go to fetch of continue.
PROFESSOR: Done.
PROFESSOR: OK.
All right.
Well, that's the basic idea.
That's a simple operation
of the machine.
Now, let's actually do something
a little bit more
interesting.
Let's look at the expression
the sum of x and y.
OK.
And now we'll see how you
start unrolling these
expression trees, OK?
Well, start again at
eval-dispatch, all right?
Self-evaluating?
No.
Variable?
All the other special forms
which I didn't write down,
like quote, and lambda,
and set, and whatever,
it's none of those.
It turns out to be an
application, so we go off to
ev-application, OK?
Ev-application, remember what
it's going to do overall.
It is going to evaluate
the operator.
It's going to evaluate the
arguments, and then it's going
to go apply them.
So, before we start, since we're
being very literal, we'd
better remember that, somewhere
in this environment,
it's linked to another
environment in which plus is
bound to the primitive procedure
plus before we get
an unknown variable
in our machine.
OK, so we're at ev-application.
OK, assign to UNEV the operands
of what's in the
expression register, OK?
Those are the operands.
UNEV's a temporary register
where we're
going to save them.
PROFESSOR: I'm assigning.
PROFESSOR: Assign to
x the operator.
Now, notice we've destroyed that
expression in x, but the
piece that we need is
now in UNEV. OK.
Now, we're going to get
set up to recursively
evaluate the operator.
Save the continue register
on the stack.
Save the environment.
Save UNEV. OK, assign
to continue a
label called eval-args.
Now, what have we done?
We've set up for a
recursive call.
We're about to go to
eval-dispatch.
We've set up for a recursive
call to eval-dispatch.
What did we do?
We took the things we're going
to need later, those operands
that were in UNEV; the
environment in which we're
going to eventually have to,
maybe, evaluate those
operands; the place we
eventually want to go to,
which, in this case, was done;
we've saved them on the stack.
The reason we saved them
on the stack is because
eval-dispatch makes no promises
about what registers
it may destroy.
So all that stuff is
saved on the stack.
Now, we've set up
eval-dispatch's contract.
There's a new expression, which
is the operator plus; a
new environment, although, in
this case, it's the same one;
and a new place to
go to when you're
done, which is eval-args.
So that's set up.
Now, we're going to go
off to eval-dispatch.
Here we are back at
eval-dispatch.
It's not self-evaluating.
Oh, it's a variable, so
we'd better go off to
ev-variable, right?
Ev-variable is assigned
to VAL.
Look up the variable value
of the expression, OK?
So VAL is the primitive
procedure plus, OK?
And go to fetch of continue.
PROFESSOR: Eval-args.
PROFESSOR: Right, which is
now eval-args not done.
So we come back here at
eval-args, and what do we do?
We're going to restore the stuff
that we saved, so we
restore UNEV. And notice, there,
it wasn't necessary,
although, in general,
it would be.
It might be some arbitrary
evaluation that happened.
We restore ENV. OK, we assign
to FUN fetch of VAL.
OK, now, we're going
to go off and start
evaluating some arguments.
Well, first thing we'd better
do is save FUN because some
arbitrary stuff might happen
in that evaluation.
We initialize the argument list.
Assign to argl an empty
argument list, and go to
eval-arg-loop, OK?
At eval-arg-loop, the idea
of this is we're going to
evaluate the pieces of the
expressions that are in UNEV,
one by one, and move them from
unevaluated in UNEV to
evaluated in the arg list, OK?
So we save argl.
We assign to x the first operand
of the stuff in UNEV.
Now, we check and see if that
was the last operand.
In this case, it is
not, all right?
So we save the environment.
We save UNEV because those
are all things
we might need later.
We're going to need the
environment to do some more
evaluations.
We're going to need UNEV to look
at what the rest of those
arguments were.
We're going to assign continue
a place called
accumulate-args, or
accumulate-arg.
OK, now, we've set up
for another call to
eval-dispatch, OK?
All right, now, let me
short-circuit this so we don't
go through the details
of eval-dispatch.
Eval-dispatch's contract says
I'm going to end up, the world
will end up, with the value of
evaluating this expression in
this environment in
the VAL register,
and I'll end up there.
So we short-circuit all of this,
and a 3 ends up in VAL.
And, when we return from
eval-dispatch, we're going to
return to accumulate-arg.
PROFESSOR: Accumulate-arg.
PROFESSOR: With 3 in the
VAL register, OK?
So that short-circuited
that evaluation.
Now, what do we do?
We're going to go back and
look at the rest of the
arguments, so we restore
UNEV. We restore
ENV. We restore argl.
One thing.
PROFESSOR: Oops!
Parity error.
[LAUGHTER]
PROFESSOR: Restore argl.
PROFESSOR: OK.
OK, we assign to argl consing on
fetch of the value register
to what's in argl.
OK, we assign to UNEV the rest
of the operands in fetch of
UNEV, and we go back
to eval-arg-loop.
PROFESSOR: Eval-arg-loop.
PROFESSOR: OK.
Now, we're about to do the next
argument, so the first
thing we do is save argl.
OK, we assign to x the first
operand of fetch of UNEV. OK,
we test and see if that's
the last operand.
In this case, it is, so we're
going to go to a special place
that says evaluate the last
argument because, notice,
after evaluating the argument,
we don't need the
environment any more.
That's going to be
the difference.
So here, at eval-last-arg,
which is assigned to
accumulate-last-arg, now,
we're set up again for
eval-dispatch.
We've got a place to go
to when we're done.
We've got an expression.
We've got an environment.
OK, so we'll short-circuit the
call to eval-dispatch.
And what'll happen is there's
a y there, it's 4 in that
environment, so VAL will
end up with 4 in it.
And, then, we're going to end up
at accumulate-last-arg, OK?
So, at accumulate-last-arg,
we restore argl.
We assign to argl cons of fetch
of the new value onto
it, so we cons a 4 onto that.
We restore what was saved in
the function register.
And notice, in this case, it had
not been destroyed, but,
in general, it will be.
And now, we're ready to go off
to apply-dispatch, all right?
So we've just gone
through the eval.
We evaluated the argument, the
operator, and the arguments,
and now, we're about
to apply them.
So we come off to apply-dispatch
here, OK?
We come off to apply-dispatch,
and we're going to check
whether it's a primitive or
a compound procedure.
PROFESSOR: Yes.
PROFESSOR: All right.
So, in this case, it's a
primitive procedure, and we go
off to primitive-apply.
So we go off to primitive-apply,
and it says
assign to VAL the result of
applying primitive procedure
of the function to the
argument list.
PROFESSOR: I don't
know how to add.
I'm just an execution unit.
PROFESSOR: Well, I don't
know how to add either.
I'm just the evaluator, so we
need a primitive operator.
Let's see, so the primitive
operator, what's the
sum of 3 and 4?
AUDIENCE: 7.
PROFESSOR: OK, 7.
PROFESSOR: Thank you.
PROFESSOR: Now, we restore
continue, and we go to fetch
of continue.
PROFESSOR: Done.
PROFESSOR: OK.
Well, that was in as much detail
as you will ever see.
We'll never do it in as
much detail again.
One very important thing to
notice is that we just
executed a recursive
procedure, right?
This whole thing, we used
a stack and the
evaluator was recursive.
A lot of people think the reason
that you need a stack
and recursion in an evaluator
is because you might be
evaluating recursive
procedures like
factorial or Fibonacci.
It's not true.
So you notice we did recursion
here, and all we evaluated was
plus X, Y, all right?
The reason that you need
recursion in the evaluator is
because the evaluation
process, itself, is
recursive, all right?
It's not because the procedure
that you might be evaluating
in LISP is a recursive
procedure.
So that's an important
thing that people get
confused about a lot.
The other thing to notice is
that, when we're done here,
we're really done.
Not only are we at done, but
there's no accumulated stuff
on the stack, right?
The machine is back to its
initial state, all right?
So that's part of what
it means to be done.
Another way to say that is the
evaluation process has reduced
the expression, plus X, Y,
to the value here, 7.
And by reduced, I mean a
very particular thing.
It means that there's nothing
left on the stack.
The machine is now in the same
state, except there's
something in the
value register.
It's not part of a sub-problem
of anything.
There's nothing to go back to.
OK.
Let's break.
Question?
AUDIENCE: The question here, in
the stack, is because the
data may be recursive.
You may have embedded
expressions, for instance.
PROFESSOR: Yes, because you
might have embedded
expressions.
But, again, don't confuse that
with what people sometimes
mean by the data may be
recursive, which is to say you
have these list-structured,
recursive data list
operations.
That has nothing
to do with it.
It's simply that the
expressions contain
sub-expressions.
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: Why is it that the
order of the arguments in the
arg list got reversed?
PROFESSOR: Ah!
Yes, I should've
mentioned that.
Here, the reason the
order is reversed--
it's a question of what
you mean by reversed.
I believe it was Newton.
In the very early part of
optics, people realized that,
when you look through the lens
of your eye, the image was
up-side down.
And there was a lot of argument
about why that didn't
mean you saw things
up-side down.
So it's sort of the
same issue.
Reversed from what?
So we just need some
convention.
The reason that they're coming
at 4, 3 is because we're
taking UNEV and consing
the result onto argl.
So you have to realize you've
made that convention.
The place that you have
to realize that--
well, there's actually
two places.
One is in
apply-primitive-operator,
which has to realize that the
arguments to primitives go in,
in the opposite order from the
way you're writing them down.
And the other one is, we'll see
later when you actually go
to bind a function's parameters,
you should realize
the arguments are going to
come in from the opposite
order of the variables to which
you're binding them.
So, if you just keep track of
that, there's no problem.
Also, this is completely
arbitrary because, if we'd
done, say, an iteration through
a vector assigning
them, they might come out
in the other order, OK?
So it's just a convention of
the way this particular
evaluator works.
All right, let's take a break.
We just saw evaluating an
expression and, of course,
that was very simple one.
But, in essence, it would be
no different if it was some
big nested expression, so there
would just be deeper
recursion on the stack.
But what I want to do now is
show you the last piece.
I want to walk you around this
eval and apply loop, right?
That's the thing we haven't
seen, really.
We haven't seen any compound
procedures where applying a
procedure reduces to evaluating
the body of the
procedure, so let's just
suppose we had this.
Suppose we were looking at the
procedure define F of A and B
to be the sum of A and B. So, as
we typed in that procedure
previously, and now we're going
to evaluate F of X and
Y, again, in this environment,
E,0, where X is bound to 3 and
Y is bound to 4.
When the defined is executed,
remember, there's a lambda
here, and lambdas create
procedures.
And, basically, what will happen
is, in E,0, we'll end
up with a binding for F, which
will say F is a procedure, and
its args are A and B, and
its body is plus a,b.
So that's what the environment
would have looked like had we
made that definition.
Then, when we go to evaluate F
of X and Y, we'll go through
exactly the same process
that we did before.
It's even the same expression.
The only difference is that F,
instead of having primitive
plus in it, will have
this thing.
And so we'll go through exactly
the same process,
except this time, when we end
up at apply-dispatch, the
function register, instead of
having primitive plus, will
have a thing that will represent
it saying procedure,
where the args are A and B,
and the body is plus A, B.
And, again, what I mean, by
its ENV, I mean there's a
pointer to it, so don't worry
that I'm writing a lot of
stuff there.
There's a pointer to this
procedure data structure.
OK, so, we're in exactly
the same situation.
We get to apply-dispatch,
so, here, we come to
apply-dispatch.
Last time, we branched off
to a primitive procedure.
Here, it says oh, we now have a
compound procedure, so we're
going to go off to
compound-apply.
Now, what's compound-apply?
Well, remember what the
meta-circular evaluator did?
Compound-apply said we're going
to evaluate the body of
the procedure in some
new environment.
Where does that new environment
come from?
We take the environment that
was packaged with the
procedure, we bind the
parameters of the procedure to
the arguments that we're passing
in, and use that as a
new frame to extend the
procedure environment.
And that's the environment
in which we evaluate the
procedure body, right?
That's going around the
apply/eval loop.
That's apply coming back to
call eval, all right?
OK.
So, now, that's all we have
to do in compound-apply.
What are we going to do?
We're going to manufacture
a new environment.
And we're going to manufacture
a new environment, let's see,
that we'll call E,1.
E,1 is going to be some
environment where the
parameters of the procedure,
where A is bound to 3 and B is
bound to 4, and it's linked
to E,0 because
that's where f is defined.
And, in this environment, we're
going to evaluate the
body of the procedure.
So let's look at that,
all right?
All right, here we are at
compound-apply, which says
assign to the expression
register the body of the
procedure that's in the
function register.
So I assign to the expression
register the
procedure body, OK?
That's going to be evaluated
in an environment which is
formed by making some bindings
using information determined
by the procedure--
that's what's in FUN--
and the argument list.
And let's not worry about
exactly what that does, but
you can see the information's
there.
So make bindings will say oh,
the procedure, itself, had an
environment attached to it.
I didn't write that
quite here.
I should've said in environment
because every
procedure gets built with
an environment.
So, from that environment, it
knows what the procedure's
definition environment is.
It knows what the
arguments are.
It looks at argl, and
then you see a
reversal convention here.
It just has to know that argl
is reversed, and it builds
this frame, E,1.
All right, so, let's assume that
that's what make bindings
returns, so it assigns to
ENV this thing, E,1.
All right, the next thing it
says is restore continue.
Remember what continue
was here?
It got put up in the
last segment.
Continue got stored.
That was the original done,
which said what are you going
to do after you're done with
this particular application?
It was one of the very first
things that happened when we
evaluated the application.
And now, finally, we're going
to restore continue.
Remember apply-dispatch's
contract.
It assumes that where it should
go to next was on the
stack, and there it
was on the stack.
Continue has done, and now
we're going to go back to
eval-dispatch.
We're set up again.
We have an expression,
an environment, and
a place to go to.
We're not going to go through
that because it's sort of the
same expression.
OK, but the thing, again, to
notice is, at this point, we
have reduced the original
expression, F,X,Y, right?
We've reduced evaluating F,X,Y
in environment E,0 to evaluate
plus A, B in E,1.
And notice, nothing's
on the stack, right?
It's a reduction.
At this point, the machine does
not contain, as part of
its state, the fact that it's
in the middle of evaluating
some procedure called f,
that's gone, right?
There's no accumulated
state, OK?
Again, that's a very
important idea.
That's the meaning of, when
we used to write in the
substitution model, this
expression reduces to that
expression.
And you don't have to
remember anything.
And here, you see the meaning
of reduction.
At this point, there is
nothing on the stack.
See, that has very important
consequences.
Let's go back and look
at iterative
factorial, all right?
Remember, this was some sort
of loop and doing iter.
And we kept saying that's an
iterative procedure, right?
And what we wrote, remember,
are things like, we said,
fact-iter of 5.
We wrote things like reduces
to iter of 1, and 1, and 5,
which reduces to iter of 1, and
2, and 5, and so on, and
so on, and so on.
And we kept saying well, look,
you don't have to build up any
storage to do that.
And we waved our hands, and said
in principle, there's no
storage needed.
Now, you see no storage
needed.
Each of these is a real
reduction, right?
As you walk through these
expressions, what you'll see
are these expressions on the
stack in some particular
environment, and then these
expressions in the EXP
register in some particular
environment.
And, at each point, there'll be
no accumulated stuff on the
stack because each one's
a real reduction, OK?
All right, so, for example,
just to go through it in a
little bit more care, if I start
out with an expression
that says something like, oh,
say, fact-iter of 5 in some
environment that will, at some
point, create an environment
in which n is down to 5.
Let's call that--
And, at some point, the machine
will reduce this whole
thing to a thing that says
that's really iter of 1, and
1, and n, evaluated in this
environment, E,1 with nothing
on the stack.
See, at this moment, the machine
is not remembering
that evaluating this
expression, iter--
which is the loop-- is
part of this thing
called iterative factorial.
It's not remembering that.
It's just reducing the
expression to that, right?
If we look again at the body of
iterative factorial, this
expression has reduced
to that expression.
Oh, I shouldn't have
the n there.
It's a slightly different
convention from the slide to
the program, OK?
And, then, what's the
body of iter?
Well, iter's going to be an it,
and I won't go through the
details of if.
It'll evaluate the predicate.
In this case, it'll be false.
And this iter will now reduce
to the expression iter of
whatever it says, star,
counter product, and--
what does it say--
plus counter 1 in some other
environment, by this time,
E,2, where E,2 will be set up
having bindings for product
and counter, right?
And it'll reduce
to that, right?
It won't be remembering that
it's part of something that it
has to return to.
And when iter calls iter again,
it'll reduce to another
thing that looks like this in
some environment, E,3, which
has new bindings for product
and counter.
So, if you're wondering, see,
if you've always been queasy
about how it is we've been
saying those procedures, that
look syntactically recursive,
are, in fact, iterative, run
in constant space, well, I don't
know if this makes you
less queasy, but at least it
shows you what's happening.
There really isn't any
buildup there.
Now, you might ask well, is
there buildup in principle in
these environment frames?
And the answer is yeah, you
have to make these new
environment frames, but you
don't have to hang onto them
when you're done.
They can be garbage collected,
or the space can be reused
automatically.
But you see the control
structure of the evaluator is
really using this idea that you
actually have a reduction,
so these procedures really
are iterative procedures.
All right, let's stop
for questions.
All right, let's break.
Let me contrast the iterative
procedure just so you'll see
where space does build up with
a recursive procedure, so you
can see the difference.
Let's look at the evaluation
of recursive
factorial, all right?
So, here's fact-recursive, or
standard factorial definition.
We said this one is still a
recursive procedure, but this
is actually a recursive
process.
And then, just to link it back
to the way we started, we said
oh, you can see that it's going
to be recursive process
by the substitution model
because, if I say recursive
factorial of 5, that turns
into 5 times--
what is it, fact-rec,
or record fact--
5 times recursive factorial of
4, which turns into 5 times 4
times fact-rec of 3, which
returns into 5 times 4 times 3
times, and so on, right?
The idea is there was this chain
of stuff building up,
which justified, in the
substitution model, the fact
that it's recursive.
And now, let's actually see that
chain of stuff build up
and where it is in
the machine, OK?
All right, well, let's
imagine we're going
to start out again.
We'll tell it to evaluate
recursive factorial of 5 in
some environment, again, E,0
where recursive factorial is
defined, OK?
Well, now we know what's
eventually going to happen.
This is going to come along,
it'll evaluate those things,
figure out it's a procedure,
build somewhere over here an
environment, E,1, which has n
bound to 5, which hangs off of
E,0, which would be, presumably,
the definition
environment of recursive
factorial, OK?
And, in this environment,
it's going to go off and
evaluate the body.
So, again, the evaluation here
will reduce to evaluating the
body in E,1.
That's going to look at an if,
and I won't go through the
details of if.
It'll look at the predicate.
It'll decide it eventually has
to evaluate the alternative.
So this whole thing, again, will
reduce to the alternative
of recursive factorial, the
alternative clause, which says
that this whole thing reduces
to times n of recursive
factorial of n minus 1 in
the environment E,1, OK?
So the original expression,
now, is going to reduce to
evaluating that expression,
all right?
Now we have an application.
We did an application before.
Remember what happens
in an application?
The first thing you do is you go
off and you save the value
of the continue register
on the stack.
So the stack here is going
to have done in it.
And then you're going to
set up to evaluate
the sub-parts, OK?
So here we go off to evaluate
the sub-parts.
First thing we're going to do
is evaluate the operator.
What happens when we evaluate
an operator?
Well, we arrange things so that
the operator ends up in
the expression register.
The environments in the ENV
register continue someplace
where we're going to go evaluate
the arguments.
And, on the stack, we've saved
the original continue, which
is where we wanted to be
when we're all done.
And then the things we needed
when we're going to get done
evaluating the operator, the
things we'll need to evaluate
the arguments, namely, the
environment and those
arguments, those unevaluated
arguments, so there they are
sitting on the stack.
And we're about to go off to
evaluate the operator.
Well, when we return from
this particular call--
so we're about to call
eval-dispatch here--
when we return from this call,
the value of that operator,
which, in this case, is going to
be the primitive multiplier
procedure, will end up in the
FUN register, all right?
We're going to evaluate
some arguments.
They will evaluate in here.
That'll give us 5,
in this case.
We're going to put that in the
argl register, and then we'll
go off to evaluate the
second operand.
So, at the point where we go
off to evaluate the second
operand-- and I'll skip details
like computing, and
minus 1, and all of that--
but, when we go off to
evaluate the second operand,
that will eventually reduce to
another call to fact-recursive.
And, what we've got on the stack
here is the operator
from that combination that we're
going to use it in and
the other argument, OK?
So, now, we're set up
for another call
to recursive factorial.
And, when we're done with this
one, we're going to go to
accumulate the last arg.
And remember what that'll do?
That'll say oh, whatever the
result of this has to get
combined with that, and we're
going to multiply them.
But, notice now, we're at
another recursive factorial.
We're about to call
eval-dispatch again, except we
haven't really reduced it
because there's stuff
on the stack now.
The stuff on the stack says oh,
when you get back, you'd
better multiply it by the
5 you had hanging there.
So, when we go off to make
another call, we
evaluate the n minus 1.
That gives us another
environment in which the new
n's going to be down to 4.
And we're about to call
eval-dispatch again, right?
We get another call.
That 4 is going to end up
in the same situation.
We'll end up with another call
to fact-recursive n.
And sitting on the stack will be
the stuff from the original
one and, now, the subsidiary
one we're doing.
And both of them are waiting
for the same thing.
They're going to go to
accumulate a last argument.
And then, of course, when we
go to the fourth call, the
same thing happens, right?
And this goes on,
and on, and on.
And what you see here on the
stack, exactly what's sitting
here on the stack, the thing
that says times and 5.
And what you're going to do with
that is accumulate that
into a last argument.
That's exactly this, right?
This is exactly where that
stuff is hanging.
Effectively, the operator you're
going to apply, the
other argument that it's got to
be multiplied by when you
get back and the parentheses,
which says yeah, what you
wanted to do was accumulate
them.
So, you see, the substitution
model is not such a lie.
That really is, in some
sense, what's sitting
right on the stack.
OK.
All right, so that, in some
sense, should explain for you,
or at least convince you, that,
somehow, this evaluator
is managing to take these
procedures and execute some of
them iteratively and some of
them recursively, even though,
as syntactically, they look
like recursive procedures.
How's it managing to do that?
Well, the basic reason it's
managing to do that is the
evaluator is set up to save
only what it needs later.
So, for example, at the point
where you've reduced
evaluating an expression and an
environment to applying a
procedure to some arguments, it
doesn't need that original
environment anymore because any
environment stuff will be
packaged inside the procedures
where the
application's going to happen.
All right, similarly, when
you're going along evaluating
an argument list, when you've
finished evaluating the list,
when you're finished evaluating
the last argument,
you don't need that argument
list any more, right?
And you don't need the
environment where those
arguments would be
evaluated, OK?
So the basic reason that this
interpreter is being so smart
is that it's not being smart
at all, it's being stupid.
It's just saying I'm
only going to save
what I really need.
Well, let me show you here.
Here's the actual thing that's
making a tail recursive.
Remember, it's the restore
of continue.
It's saying when I go off to
evaluate the procedure body, I
should tell eval to come back
to the place where that
original evaluation was supposed
to come back to.
So, in some sense, you want to
say what's the actual line
that makes a tail recursive?
It's that one.
If I wanted to build a non-tail
recursive evaluator,
for some strange reason, all I
would need to do is, instead
of restoring continue at this
point, I'd set up a label down
here called, "Where to come
back after you've finished
applying the procedure."
Instead, I'd
set continue to that.
I'd go to eval-dispatch,
and then eval-dispatch
would come back here.
At that point, I would restore
continue and go to the
original one.
So here, the only consequence
of that would be to make it
non-tail recursive.
It would give you exactly the
same answers, except, if you
did that iterative factorial
and all those iterative
procedures, it would execute
recursively.
Well, I lied to you a little
bit, but just a little bit,
because I showed you a slightly
over-simplified
evaluator where it assumes that
each procedure body has
only one expression.
Remember, in general, a
procedure has a sequence of
expressions in it.
So there's nothing really
conceptually new.
Let me just show you the actual
evaluator that handles
sequences of expressions.
This is compound-apply now, and
the only difference from
the old one is that, instead of
going off to eval directly,
it takes the whole body of the
procedure, which, in this
case, is a sequence of
expressions, and goes off to
eval-sequence.
And eval-sequence is a little
loop that, basically, does
these evaluations
one at a time.
So it does an evaluation.
Says oh, when I come back, I'd
better come back here to do
the next one.
And, when I'm all done, when
I want to get the last
expression, I just restore
my continue and go off to
eval-dispatch.
And, again, if you wanted for
some reason to break tail
recursion in this evaluator,
all you need to do is not
handle the last expression,
especially.
Just say, after you've done the
last expression, come back
to some other place after which
you restore continue.
And, for some reason, a lot
of LISP evaluators tended
to work that way.
And the only consequence of
that is that iterative
procedures built up stack.
And it's not clear why
that happened.
All right.
Well, let me just sort of
summarize, since this is a lot
of details in a big program.
But the main point is that
it's no different,
conceptually, from translating
any other program.
And the main idea is that we
have this universal evaluator
program, the meta-circular
evaluator.
If we translate that
into LISP, then
we have all of LISP.
And that's all we did, OK?
The second point is that
the magic's gone away.
There should be no more magic
in this whole system, right?
In principle, it should all be
very clear except, maybe, for
how list structured
memory works, and
we'll see that later.
But that's not very hard.
The third point is that all this
tail recursion came from
the discipline of eval being
very careful to save only what
it needs next time.
It's not some arbitrary thing
where we're saying well,
whenever we call a sub-routine,
we'll save all
the registers in the world
and come back, right?
See, sometimes it pays to really
worry about efficiency.
And, when you're down in the
guts of your evaluator
machine, it really pays to think
about things like that
because it makes big
consequences.
Well, I hope what this has
done is really made the
evaluator seem concrete,
right?
I hope you really believe that
somebody could hold a LISP
evaluator in the palm
of their hand.
Maybe to help you believe that,
here's a LISP evaluator
that I'm holding the palm
of my hand, right?
And this is a chip which is
actually quite a bit more
complicated than the evaluator
I showed you.
Maybe, here's a better
picture of it.
What there is, is you can see
the same overall structure.
This is a register array.
These are the data paths.
Here's a finite state
controller.
And again, finite state,
that's all there is.
And somewhere there's
external memory
that'll worry about things.
And this particular one is very
complicated because it's
trying to run LISP fast. And
it has some very, very fast
parallel operations in there
like, if you want to index
into an array, simultaneously
check that the index is an
integer, check that it doesn't
exceed the array bands, and go
off and do the memory access,
and do all those things
simultaneously.
And then, later, if they're
all OK, actually
get the value there.
So there are a lot of
complicated operations in
these data paths for making
LISP run in parallel.
It's a completely non-risk
philosophy of evaluating LISP.
And then, this microcode
is pretty complicated.
Let's see, there's what?
There's about 389 instructions
of 220-bit microcode sitting
here because these are very
complicated data paths.
And the whole thing has about
89,000 transistors, OK?
OK.
Well, I hope that that takes
away a lot of the mystery.
Maybe somebody wants
to look at this.
Yeah.
OK.
Let's stop.
Questions?
AUDIENCE: OK, now, it sounds
like what you're saying is
that, with the restore continue
put in the proper
place, that procedures that
would invoke a recursive
process now invoke an integer
process just by the way that
the eval signature is?
PROFESSOR: I think the way I'd
prefer to put it is that, with
restore continue put in the
wrong place, you can cause any
syntactically-looking recursive
procedure, in fact,
to build up stack as it runs.
But there's no reason for that,
so you might want to
play around with it.
You can just switch around two
or three instructions in the
way compound-apply comes back,
and you'll get something which
isn't tail recursive.
But the thing I wanted to
emphasize is there's no magic.
It's not as if there's some
very clever pre-processing
program that's looking at this
procedure, factorial iter, and
say oh, gee, I really notice
that I don't have to push
stack in order to do this.
Some people think that that's
what's going on.
It's something much, much more
dumb than that, it's this one
place you're putting the
restore instruction.
It's just automatic.
AUDIENCE: OK.
AUDIENCE: But that's not
affecting the time
complexity is it?
PROFESSOR: No.
AUDIENCE: It's just that it's
handling it recursively
instead of iteratively.
But, in terms of the order of
time it takes to finish the
operation, it's the same one
way or the other, right?
PROFESSOR: Yes.
Tail recursion is not going to
change the time complexity of
anything because, in some sense,
it's the same algorithm
that's going on.
What it's doing is really making
this thing run as an
iteration, right?
Not going to run out of memory
counting up to a giant number
simply because the stack
would get pushed.
See, the thing you really
have to believe is
that, when we write--
see, we've been writing all
these things called
iterations, infinite loops,
define loop to be called loop.
That's is as much an iteration
as if we wrote do forever
loop, right?
It's just syntactic sugar
as the difference.
These things are real, honest
to god, iterations, right?
They don't change the time
complexity, but they turn them
into real iterations.
All right, thank you.