PROFESSOR: Well, now that we've
given you some power to
make independent local state
and to model objects, I
thought we'd do a bit of
programming of a very
complicated kind, just to
illustrate what you can do
with this sort of thing.
I suppose, as I said, we were
motivated by physical systems
and the ways we like to think
about physical systems, which
is that there are these things
that the world is made out of.
And each of these things has
particular independent local
state, and therefore
it is a thing.
That's what makes it a thing.
And then we're going to say
that in the model in the
world--we have a world and a
model in our minds and in the
computer of that world.
And what I want to make is a
correspondence between the
objects in the world and the
objects in the computer, the
relationships between the
objects in the world and the
relationships between those same
obj...--the model objects
in the computer, and the
functions that relate things
in the world to the functions
that relate
things in the computer.
This buys us modularity.
If we really believe the world
is like that, that it's made
out of these little pieces, and
of course we could arrange
our world to be like that, we
could only model those things
that are like that, then we can
inherit the modularity in
the world into our
programming.
That's why we would invent some
of this object-oriented
programming.
Well, let's take the best
kind of objects I know.
They're completely--they're
completely wonderful:
electrical systems. Electrical
systems really are the
physicist's best,
best objects.
You see over here I have some
piece of machinery.
Right here's a piece
of machinery.
And it's got an electrical wire
connecting one part of
the machinery with another
part of the machinery.
And one of the wonderful
properties of the electrical
world is that I can say this is
an object, and this is an
object, and they're--
the connection between
them is clear.
In principle, there is no
connection that I didn't
describe with these wires.
Let's say if I have light bulbs,
a light bulb and a
power supply that's plugged
into the outlet.
Then the connection is
perfectly clear.
There's no other connections
that we know of.
If I were to tie a knot in the
wire that connects the light
bulb to the power supply, the
light remains lit up.
It doesn't care.
That the way the physics is
arranged is such that the
connection can be made abstract,
at least for low
frequencies and things
like that.
So in fact, we have captured all
of the connections there
really are.
Well, as you can go one step
further and talk about the
most abstract types of
electrical systems we have,
digital to dual circuits.
And here there are certain
kinds of objects.
For example, in digital
circuits we
have things like inverters.
We have things like and-gates.
We have things like or-gates.
We connect them together by
sort-of wires which represent
abstract signals.
We don't really care as physical
variables whether
these are voltages or currents
or some combination or
anything like that, or water,
water pressure.
These abstract variables
represent certain signals.
And we build systems by
wiring these things
together with wires.
So today what I'm going to show
you, right now, we're
going to build up an invented
language in Lisp, embedded in
the same sense that Henderson's
picture language
was embedded, which is not the
same sense as the language of
pattern match and substitution
was done yesterday.
The pattern match/substitution
language was interpreted by a
Lisp program.
But the embedding of Henderson's
program is that we
just build up more and more
procedures that encapsulate
the structure we want.
So for example here, I'm going
to have some various primitive
kinds of objects, as you see,
that one and that one.
I'm going to use wires
to combine them.
The way I represent
attaching--
I can make wires.
So let's say A is a wire.
And B is a wire.
And C is a wire.
And D is a wire.
And E is wire.
And S is a wire.
Well, an or-gate that has both
inputs, the inputs being A and
B, and the output being Y or
D, you notate like this.
An and-gate, which has inputs
A and B and output C, we
notate like that.
By making such a sequence of
declarations, like this, I can
wire together an arbitrary
circuit.
So I've just told you a set
of primitives and means of
combination for building digital
circuits, when I need
more in a real language
than abstraction.
And so for example,
here I have--here
I have a half adder.
It's something you all
know if you've
done any digital design.
It's used for adding numbers
together on A and B and
putting out a sum and a carry.
And in fact, the wiring
diagram is
exactly what I told you.
A half adder with things that
come out of the box-- you see
the box, the boundary, the
abstraction is always a box.
And there are things that come
out of it, A, B, S, and C.
Those are the declared
variables--declared variables
of a lambda expression,
which is the one that
defines half adder.
And internal to that, I make up
some more wires, D and E,
which I'm going to use for
the interconnect--
here E is this one and D is this
wire, the interconnect
that doesn't come through
the walls of the box--
and wire things together
as you just saw.
And the nice thing about this
that I've just shown you is
this language is hierarchical
in the right way.
If a language isn't hierarchical
in the right way,
if it turns out that a compound
object doesn't look
like a primitive, there's
something
wrong with the language--
at least the way I
feel about that.
So here we have--here, instead
of starting with mathematical
functions, or things that
compute mathematical
functions, which is what we've
been doing up until now,
instead of starting with
things that look like
mathematical functions, or
compute such things, we are
starting with things that are
electrical objects and we
build up more electrical
objects.
And the glue we're using
is basically the
Lisp structure: lambdas.
Lambda is the ultimate
glue, if you will.
And of course, half adder itself
can be used in a more
complicated abstraction called
a full adder, which in fact
involves two half adders, as you
see here, hooked together
with some extra wires, that you
see here, S, C1, and C2,
and an or-gate, to manufacture
a full adder, which takes a
input number, another input
number, a carry in, and
produces output, a sum
and a carry out.
And out of full adders, you can
make real adder chains and
big adders.
So we have here a language so
far that has primitives, means
of combination, and means of
abstraction to real language.
Now, how are we going
to implement this?
Well, let's do it easily.
Let's look at the primitives.
The only problem is we have to
implement the primitives.
Nothing else has to be
implemented, because we're
picking up the means of
combination and abstraction
from Lisp, inheriting them
in the embedding.
OK, so let's look at a
particular primitive.
An inverter is a nice one.
Now, inverter has two wires
coming in, an in and an out.
And somehow, it's going to have
to know what to do when a
signal comes in.
So somehow it's going to have
to tell its input wire--
and now we're going to talk
about objects and we're going
to see this in a little
more detail soon--
but it's going to have to tell
its input wire that when you
change, tell me.
So this object, the object which
is the inverter has to
tell the object which
is the input wire,
hi, my name is George.
And my, my job is to do
something with results when
you change.
So when you change, you get a
change, tell me about it.
Because I've got to do
something with that.
Well, that's done down here by
adding an action on the input
wire called invert-in, where
invert-in is defined over here
to be a procedure of no
arguments, which gets the
logical not of the signal
on the input wire.
And after some delay, which is
the inverter delay, all these
electrical objects have delays,
we'll do the following
thing-- set the signal on the
output wire to the new value.
A very simple program.
Now, you have to imagine that
the output wire has to be
sensitive and know that when
its signal changes, it may
have to tell other guys,
hey, wake up.
My value has changed.
So when you hook together
inverter with an and-gate or
something like that, there has
to be a lot of communication
going on in order to
make sure that the
signal propagates right.
And down here is nothing
very exciting.
This is just the definition
of logical not for some
particular representations
of the logical values--
1, 0 in this case.
And we can look at things more
complicated like and-gates.
And-gates take two inputs, A1
and A2, we'll call them, and
produce an output.
But the structure of the
and-gate is identical to the
one we just saw.
There's one called an and-action
procedure that's
defined, which is the thing that
gets called when an input
is changed.
And what it does, of course, is
nothing more than compute
the logical and of the signals
on the inputs.
And after some delay, called the
and-gate delay, calls this
procedure, which sets a signal
on the output to a new value.
Now, how I implement
these things
is all wishful thinking.
As you see here, I have an
assignment operation.
It's not set.
It's a derived assignment
operation in the same way we
had functions that were derived
from CAR and CDR. So
I, by convention, label that
with an exclamation point.
And over here, you see there's
an action, which is to inform
the wire, called A1 locally in
this and-gate, to call the
and-action procedure when it
gets changed, and the wire A2
to call the and-action
procedure
when it gets changed.
All very simple.
Well, let's talk a little bit
about this communication that
must occur between these
various parts.
Suppose, for example, I have
a very simple circuit which
contains an and with wires A
and B. And that connects
through a wire called C to an
inverter which has a wire
output called D. What are
the comput...--here's
the physical world.
It's an abstraction of
Now I can buy these out of
little pieces that you get at
Radio Shack for a few cents.
And there are boxes that act
like this, which have little
numbers on them like
LS04 or something.
Now supposing I were to
try to say what's the
computational model.
What is the thing that
corresponds to that, that part
of reality in the mind of
us and in the computer?
Well, I have to assign for every
object in the world an
object in the computer, and for
every relationship in the
world between them a
relationship in the computer.
That's my goal.
So let's do that.
Well, I have some sort of thing
called the signal, A.
This is A. It's a signal.
It's a cloudy thing like that.
And I have another one down here
which I'm going to call
B. It's another signal.
Now this signal--these two
signals are somehow going to
have to hook together into a
box, let's call it this, which
is the and-gate, action
procedure.
That's the and-gate's
action procedure.
And it's going to produce--well,
it's going to
interact with a signal object,
which we call C--a wire
object, excuse me, we call
C. And then the--
this is going to put out again,
or connect to, another
action procedure which is one
associated with the inverter
in the world, not.
And I'm going to have
another--another wire, which
we'll call D.
So here's my layout of stuff.
Now we have to say what's inside
them and what they have
to know to compute.
Well, every--every one of these
wires has to know what
the value of the signal that's
on that wire is.
So there's going to be some
variable inside here, we'll
call it signal.
And he owns a value.
So there must be some
environment
associated with this.
And for each one of these, there
must be an environment
that binds signal.
And there must be a signal
here, therefore.
And presumably, signal's a value
that's either 1 or 0,
and signal.
Now, we also have to have some
list of people to inform if
the signal here changes.
We're going to have
to inform this.
So I've got that list.
We'll call it the
Action Procedures, AP.
And it's presumably a list.
But the first thing on the
list, in this case,
is this guy.
And the action procedures of
this one happens to have some
list of stuff.
There might be other people
who are sharing A, who are
looking at it.
So there might be other guys
on this list, like somebody
over there that we
don't know about.
It's the other guy
attached to A.
And the action procedure here
also has to point to that, the
list of action procedures.
And of course, that means this
one, its action procedures has
to point up to here.
This is the things--
the people it has to inform.
And this guy has some too.
But I don't know what they
are because I didn't
draw it in my diagram.
It's the things connected
to D.
Now, it's also the case that
when the and-action procedure
is awakened, saying one of the
people who know that you've
told--one of the people you've
told to wake you up if their
signal changes, you have to go
look and ask them what's their
signal so you can do the
and, and produce a
signal for this one.
So there has to be, for example,
information here
saying A1, my A1 is this guy,
and my A2 is this guy.
And not only that, when I do my
and, I'm going to have to
tell this guy something.
So I need an output--
being this guy.
And similarly, this guy's going
to have a thing called
the input that he interrogates
to find out what the value of
the signal on the input is, when
the signal wakes up and
says, I've changed, and sends
a message this way saying,
I've changed.
This guy says, OK, what's
your value now?
When he gets that value, then
he's going to have to say, OK,
output changes this guy,
changes this guy.
And so on.
And so I have to have at least
that much connected-ness.
Now, let's go back and look, for
example, at the and-gate.
Here we are back
on this slide.
And we can see some
of these parts.
For any particular and-gate,
there is an A1, there is an
A2, and the output.
And those are, those are an
environment that was created
at the--those produce a frame
at the time and-gate was
called, a frame where A1, A2,
and output are--have as their
values, they're bound to the
wires which, they are--which
were passed in.
In that environment, I
constructed a procedure--
this one right there.
And-action procedure was
constructed in that
environment.
That was the result of
evaluating a lambda
expression.
So it hangs onto the frame
where these were defined.
Local--part of its local
state is that.
The and-action procedure,
therefore, has access to A1,
A2, and output as we see here.
A1, A2, and output.
Now, we haven't looked
inside of a wire yet.
That's all that remains.
Let's look at a wire.
Like the overhead, very good.
Well, the wire, again,
is a, is a
somewhat complicated mess.
Ooh, wrong one.
It's a big complicated
mess, like that.
But let's look at it in detail
and see what's going on.
Well, the wire is
one of these.
And it has to have two things
that are part of
it, that it's state.
One of them is the signal
we see here.
In other words, when we call
make-wire to make a wire, then
the first thing we do is we
create some variables which
are the signal and the action
procedures for this wire.
And in that context, we define
various functions--or
procedures, excuse
me, procedures.
One of them is called
set-my-signal to a new value.
And what that does is takes
a new value in.
If that's equal to my current
value of my signal, I'm done.
Otherwise, I set the signal to
the new value and call each of
the action procedures that
I've been, that I've
been--what's the right word?--
introduced to.
I get introduced when the
and-gate was applied to me.
I add action procedure
at the bottom.
Also, I have to define a way
of accepting an action
procedure-- which is what
you see here---
which increments my action
procedures using set to the
result of CONSing up a new
process--a procedure, which is
passed to me, on to my actions
procedures list. And for
technical reasons, I have to
call that procedure one.
So I'm not going to tell you
anything about that, that has
to do with event-driven
simulations and getting them
started, which takes a little
bit of thinking.
And finally, I'm going to define
a thing called the
dispatcher, which is a way of
passing a message to a wire,
which is going to be used to
extract from it various
information, like what is the
current signal value?
What is the method of
setting your signal?
I want to get that out of it.
How do I--how do I add another
action procedure?
And I'm going to return
that dispatch, that
procedure as a value.
So the wire that I've
constructed is a message
accepting object which accepts
a message like, like what's
your method of adding
action procedures?
In fact, it'll give me a
procedure, which is the add
action procedure, which I can
then apply to an action
procedure to create another
action procedure in the wire.
So that's a permission.
So it's given me permission to
change your action procedures.
And in fact, you can
see that over here.
Next slide.
Ah.
This is nothing very
interesting.
The call each of the action
procedures is just a CDRing
down a list. And I'm
not going to even
talk about that anymore.
We're too advanced for that.
However, if I want to
get a signal from a
wire, I ask the wire--
which is, what is the wire?
The wire is the dispatch
returned by creating the wire.
It's a procedure.
I call that dispatch on the
message get-signal.
And what I should expect
to get is a method
of getting a signal.
Or actually, I get the signal.
If I want to set a signal, I
want to change a signal, then
what I'm going to do is take a
wire as an argument and a new
value for the signal, I'm going
to ask the wire for
permission to set its signal and
use that permission, which
is a procedure, on
the new value.
And if we go back to the
overhead here, thank you, if
we go back to the overhead here,
we see that the method--
if I ask for the method of
setting the signal, that's
over here, it's set-my-signal,
a procedure that's defined
inside the wire, which if we
look over here is the thing
that says set my internal value
called the signal, my
internal variable, which is the
signal, to the new value,
which is passed to me as an
argument, and then call each
of the action procedures
waking them up.
Very simple.
Going back to that slide, we
also have the one last thing--
which I suppose now you can
easily work out for yourself--
is the way you add an action.
You take a wire--a wire and
an action procedure.
And I ask the wire for
permission to add an action.
Getting that permission, I use
that permission to give it an
action procedure.
So that's a real object.
There's a few more details
about this.
For example, how am I going
to control this thing?
How do I do these delays?
Let's look at that
for a second.
The next one here.
Let's see.
We know when we looked at the
and-gate or the not-gate that
when a signal changed on the
input, there was a delay.
And then it was going to call
the procedure, which was going
to change the output.
Well, how are we going
to do this?
We're going to make up some
mechanism, a fairly
complicated mechanism at that,
which we're going to have to
be very careful about.
But after a delay, we're
going to do an action.
A delay is a number, and an
action is a procedure.
What that's going to be is
they're going to have a
special structure called an
agenda, which is a thing that
organizes time and actions.
And we're going to see
that in a while.
I don't want to get into
that right now.
But the agenda has a
moment at which--at
which something happens.
We're setting up for later at
some moment, which is the sum
of the time, which is the delay
time plus the current
time, which the agenda
thinks is now.
We're going to set up to do this
action, and add that to
the agenda.
And the way this machine will
now run is very simple.
We have a thing called
propagate, which is the way
things run.
If the agenda is empty, we're
done--if there's nothing more
to be done.
Otherwise, we're going to take
the first item off the agenda,
and that's a procedure
of no arguments.
So that we're going to see
extra parentheses here.
We call that on no arguments.
That takes the action.
Then we remove that first item
from the agenda, and we go
around the propagation loop.
So that's the overall structure
of this thing.
Now, there's a, a few other
things we can look at.
And then we're going to
look into the agenda a
little while from now.
Now the overhead again.
Well, in order to set this thing
going, I just want to
show you some behavior out
of this simulator.
By the way, you may think this
simulator is very simple, and
probably too simple
to be useful.
The fact of the matter is that
this simulator has been used
to manufacture a fairly
large computer.
So this is a real
live example.
Actually, not exactly this
simulator, because I'll tell
you the difference.
The difference is that there
were many more different kinds
of primitives.
There's not just the word
inverter or and-gate.
There were things like
edge-triggered, flip-flops,
and latches, transparent
latches, and adders, and
things like that.
And the difficulty with that
is that there's pages and
pages of the definitions of
all these primitives with
numbers like LS04.
And then there's many more
parameters for them.
It's not just one delay.
There's things like set
up times and hold
times and all that.
But with the exception of that
part of the complexity, the
structure of the simulator that
we use for building a
real computer, that works
is exactly what
you're seeing here.
Well in any case, what we have
here is a few simple things.
Like, there's inverter delays
being set up and
making a new agenda.
And then we can make
some inputs.
There's input-1, input-2,
a sum and a
carry, which are wires.
I'm going to put a special kind
of object called a probe
onto, onto some of the wires,
onto sum and onto carry.
A probe is a, can object that
has the property that when you
change a wire it's attached to,
it types out a message.
It's an easy thing to do.
And then once we have that, of
course, the way you put the
probe on, the first thing it
does, it says, the current
value of the sum at time 0 is
0 because I just noticed it.
And the value of the carry
at time 0, this is
the time, is 0.
And then we go off and we
build some structure.
Like, we can build a structure
here that says you have a
half-adder on input-1, input-2,
sum, and carry.
And we're going to set the
signal on input-1 to 1.
We do some propagation.
At time 8, which you could see
going through this thing if
you wanted to, the new value
of sum became 1.
And the thing says I'm done.
That wasn't very interesting.
But we can send it some
more signals.
Like, we set-signal on
input-2 to be one.
And at that time if we
propagate, then it carried at
11, the carry becomes 1, and
at 16, the sum's new
value becomes 0.
And you might want to work out
that, if you like, about the
digital circuitry.
It's true, and it works.
And it's not very interesting.
But that's the kind
of behavior we
get out of this thing.
So what I've shown you right now
is a large-scale picture,
how you, at a bigger, big
scale, you implement an
event-driven simulation
of some sort.
And how you might organize it
to have nice hierarchical
structure allowing you to build
abstract boxes that you
can instantiate.
But I haven't told you any of
the details about how this
agenda and things
like that work.
That we'll do next.
And that's going to involve
change and mutation of data
and things like that.
Are there any questions
now, before I go on?
Thank you.
Let's take a break.
Well, we've been making
a simulation.
And the simulation is an
event-driven simulation where
the objects in the world are the
objects in the computer.
And the changes of state that
are happening in the world in
time are organized to be time
in the computer, so that if
something happens after
something else in the world,
then we have it happen after,
after the corresponding events
happen in the same order
in the computer.
That's where we have
assignments, when
we make that alignment.
Right now I want to show you a
way of organizing time, which
is an agenda or priority queue,
it's sometimes called.
We'll do some--we'll do
a little bit of just
understanding what are the
things we need to be able to
do to make agendas.
And so we're going to have--and
so right now over
here, I'm going to write down
a bunch of primitive
operations for manipulating
agendas.
I'm not going to show you the
code for them because they're
all very simple, and you've got
listings of all that anyway.
So what do we have?
We have things like make-agenda
which produces a
new agenda.
We can ask--we get the
current-time of an agenda,
which gives me a
number, a time.
We can get--we can ask whether
an agenda is empty,
empty-agenda.
And that produces either
a true or a false.
We can add an object
to an agenda.
Actually, what we add to an
agenda is an operation--an
action to be done.
And that takes a time, the
action itself, and the agenda
I want to add it to.
That inserts it in
the appropriate
place in the agenda.
I can get the first item off an
agenda, the first thing I
have to do, which is going
to give me an action.
And I can remove the first
item from an agenda.
That's what I have to be able
to do with agendas.
That is a big complicated
mess.
From an agenda.
Well, let's see how we can
organize this thing as a data
structure a bit.
Well, an agenda is going to be
some kind of list. And it's
going to be a list that
I'm going to have
to be able to modify.
So we have to talk about
modifying of lists, because
I'm going to add things to it,
and delete things from it, and
things like that.
It's organized by time.
It's probably good to keep
it in sorted order.
But sometimes there are lots of
things that happen at the
same time--approximate
same time.
What I have to do is say, group
things by the time at
which they're supposed
to happen.
So I'm going to make an agenda
as a list of segments.
And so I'm going to draw you a
data structure for an agenda,
a perfectly reasonable one.
Here's an agenda.
It's a thing that begins
with a name.
I'm going to do it right now
out of list structure.
It's got a header.
There's a reason
for the header.
We're going to see
the reason soon.
And it will have a segment.
It will have--it will be
a list of segments.
Supposing this agenda has two
segments, they're the car's--
successive car's of this
list. Each segment is
going to have a time--
say for example, 10--
that says that the things
that happen in this
segment are at time 10.
And what I'm going to have in
here is another data structure
which I'm not going to describe,
which is a queue of
things to do at time 10.
It's a queue.
And we'll talk about
that in a second.
But abstractly, the queue is
just a list of things to do at
a particular time.
And I can add things
to a queue.
This is a queue.
There's a time, there's
a segment.
Now, I may have another segment
in this agenda.
Supposing this is stuff that
happens at time 30.
It has, of course, another
queue of things that are
queued up to be done
at time 30.
Well, there are various
things I have to be
able to do to an agenda.
Supposing I want to add to an
agenda another thing to be
done at time 10.
Well, that's not very hard.
I'm going to walk down
here, looking for the
segment of time 10.
It is possible that there is
no segment of time 10.
We'll cover that case
in a second.
But if I find a segment of time
10, then if I want to add
another thing to be done
at time 10, I just
increase that queue--
"just increase" isn't such
an obvious idea.
But I increase the things
to be done at that time.
Now, supposing I want to
add something to be
done at time 20.
There is no segment
for time 20.
I'm going to have to create
a new segment.
I want my time 20 segment
to exist between
time 10 and time 30.
Well, that takes
a little work.
I'm going to have
to do a CONS.
I'm going to have to make a
new element of the agenda
list--list of segments.
I'm going to have to change.
Here's change.
I'm going to have to change
the CDR of the CDR of the
agenda to point that a new CONS
of the new segment and
the CDR of the CDR of the CDR of
the agenda, the CD-D-D-DR.
And this is going to have a
new segment now of time 20
with its own queue, which now
has one element in it.
If I wanted to add something at
the end, I'm going to have
to replace the CDR of this, of
this list with something.
We're going to have to change
that piece of data structure.
So I'm going to need new
primitives for doing this.
But I'm just showing you
why I need them.
And finally, if I wanted to add
a thing to be done at time
5, I'm going to have to change
this one, because I'm going to
have to add it in over here,
which is why I planned ahead
and had a header cell,
which has a place.
If I'm going to change things,
I have to have
places for the change.
I have to have a place
to make the change.
If I remove things from the
agenda, that's not so hard.
Removing them from the beginning
is pretty easy,
which is the only case I have.
I can go looking for the
first, the first segment.
I see if it has a
non-empty queue.
If it has a non-empty queue,
well, I'm going to delete one
element from the queue,
like that.
If the queue ever becomes empty,
then I have to delete
the whole segment.
And then this, this changes
to point to here.
So it's quite a complicated data
structure manipulation
going on, the details of which
are not really very exciting.
Now, let's talk about queues.
They're similar.
Because each of these agendas
has a queue in it.
What's a queue?
A queue is going to have
the following primitive
operations.
To make a queue, this gives
me a new queue.
I'm going to have to be
able to insert into
a queue a new item.
I'm going to have to be able
to delete from a queue the
first item in the queue.
And I want to be able to get the
first thing in the queue
from some queue.
I also have to be able to test
whether a queue is empty.
And when you invent things like
this, I want you to be
very careful to use the kinds
of conventions I use for
naming things.
Notice that I'm careful to say
these change something and
that tests it.
And presumably, I did the
same thing over here.
OK, and there should be an
empty test over here.
OK, well, how would
I make a queue?
A queue wants to be something
I can add to at the end of,
and pick up the thing
at the beginning of.
I should be able to delete
from the beginning
and add to the end.
Well, I'm going to show
you a very simple
structure for that.
We can make this out
of CONSes as well.
Here's a queue.
It has--it has a queue header,
which contains two parts--
a front pointer and
a rear pointer.
And here I have a queue
with two items in it.
The first item, I don't know,
it's perhaps a 1.
And the second item, I don't
know, let's give it a 2.
The reason why I want two
pointers in here, a front
pointer and a rear pointer,
is so I can add to the end
without having to chase down
from the beginning.
So for example, if I wanted to
add one more item to this
queue, if I want to add on
another item to be worried
about later, all I have to do is
make a CONS, which contains
that item, say a 3.
That's for inserting
3 into the queue.
Then I have to change this
pointer here to here.
And I have to change this one
to point to the new rear.
If I wish to take the first
element of the queue, the
first item, I just go chasing
down the front pointer until I
find the first one
and pick it up.
If I wish to delete the first
item from the queue,
delete-queue, all I do
is move the front
pointer along this way.
The new front of the
queue is now this.
So queues are very simple too.
So what you see now is that I
need a certain number of new
primitive operations.
And I'm going to give
them some names.
And then we're going to look
into how they work, and how
they're used.
We have set the CAR of some
pair, or a thing produced by
CONSing, to a new value.
And set the CDR of a pair
to a new value.
And then we're going to look
into how they work.
I needed setting CAR over
here to delete the first
element of the queue.
This is the CAR, and
I had to set it.
I had to be able to set the
CDR to be able to move the
rear pointer, or to be able to
increment the queue here.
All of the operations I did were
made out of those that I
just showed you on the, on
the last blackboard.
Good.
Let's pause the time, and take
a little break then.
When we originally introduced
pairs made out of CONS, made
by CONS, we only said a few
axioms about them, which were
of the form--
what were they--
for all X and Y, the CAR of the
CONS of X and Y is X and
the CDR of the CONS of X and Y
is Y. Now, these say nothing
about whether a CONS has an
identity like a person.
In fact, all they say is
something sort of abstract,
that a CONS is the parts
it's made out of.
And of course, two things are
made out of the same parts,
they're the same, at least
from the point of view of
these axioms.
But by introducing
assignment--
in fact, mutable data is a kind
of assignment, we have a
set CAR and a set CDR--
by introducing those, these
axioms no longer tell the
whole story.
And they're still true if
written exactly like this.
But they don't tell
the whole story.
Because if I'm going to set a
particular CAR in a particular
CONS, the questions are, well,
is that setting all CARs and
all CONSes of the same
two things or not?
If I--if we use CONSes to make
up things like rational
numbers, or things like 3 over
4, supposing I had two
three-fourths.
Are they the same one--
or are they different?
Well, in the case of numbers,
it doesn't matter.
Because there's no meaning
to changing the
denominator of a number.
What you could do is make a
number which has a different
denominator.
But the concept of changing a
number which has to have a
different denominator is sort
of a very weird, and sort of
not supported by what you
think of as mathematics.
However, when these CONSes
represent things in the
physical world, then changing
something like the CAR is like
removing a piece of
the fingernail.
And so CONSes have
an identity.
Let me show you what I mean
about identity, first of all.
Let's do some little
example here.
Supposing I define A to
the CONS of 1 and 2.
Well, what that means, first of
all, is that somewhere in
some environment I've made a
symbol A to have a value which
is a pair consisting of pointers
to a 1 and a pointer
to a 2, just like that.
Now, supposing I also say define
B to be the CONS--
it doesn't matter, but I like
it better, it's prettier--
of A and A.
Well, first of all, I'm using
the name A twice.
At this moment, I'm
going to think of
CONSes as having identity.
This is the same one.
And so what that means is I make
another pair, which I'm
going to call B. And it contains
two pointers to A. At
this point, I have three
names for this object.
A is its name.
The CAR of B is its name.
And the CDR of B is its name.
It has several aliases,
they're called.
Now, supposing I do something
like set-the-CAR, the CAR of
the CAR of B to 3.
What that means is I find the
CAR of B, that's this.
I set the CAR of that to
be 3, changing this.
I've changed A. If I were
to ask what's the
CAR of A--of A now?
I would get out 3, even though
here we see that A was the
CONS of 1 and 2.
I caused A to change
by changing B.
There is sharing here.
That's sometimes what we want.
Surely in the queues and things
like that, that's
exactly what we defined
our--organized our data
structures to facilitate--
sharing.
But inadvertent sharing,
unanticipated interactions
between objects, is the source
of most of the bugs that occur
in complicated programs. So by
introducing this possibility
of things having identity and
sharing and having multiple
names for the same thing,
we get a lot of power.
But we're going to pay
for it with lots of
complexity and bugs.
So also, for example, if I just
looked at this just to
drive that home, the CADR of
B, which has nothing to do
with even the CAR of
B, apparently.
The CADR of B, what's that?
Take that CDR of B and now
take the CAR of that.
Oh, that's 3 also.
So I can have non-local
interactions by sharing.
And I have to be very
careful of that.
Well, so far, of course, it
seems I've introduced several
different assignment
operators--
set, set CAR, set CDR. Well,
maybe I should just get rid of
set CAR and set CDR. Maybe
they're not worthwhile.
Well, the answer is that once
you let the camel's nose into
the tent, the rest
of him follows.
All I have to have is set, and
I can make all of the--all of
the bad things that
can happen.
Let's play with that
a little bit.
A couple of days ago, when we
introduced compound data, you
saw Hal show you a definition
of CONS in terms
of a message acceptor.
I'm going to show you even
a more horrible thing, a
definition of CONS in terms of
nothing but air, hot air.
What is the definition of CONS,
of the old functional
kind, in terms of purely
lambdic expressions,
procedures?
Because I'm going to then modify
this definition to get
assignment to be only one kind
of assignment, to get rid of
the set CAR and set CDR
in terms of set.
So what if I define CONS of X
and Y to be a procedure of one
argument called a message
M, which calls that
message on X and Y?
This [? idea ?] was invented by
Alonzo Church, who was the
greatest programmer of the
20th century, although he
never saw a computer.
It was done in the 1930s.
He was a logician, I suppose
at Princeton at the time.
Define CAR of X to be the result
of applying X to that
procedure of two arguments, A
and D, which selects A. I will
define CDR of X to be that
procedure, to be the result of
applying X to that procedure of
A and D, which selects D.
Now, you may not recognize this
as CAR, CDR, and CONS.
But I'm going to demonstrate to
you that it satisfies the
original axioms, just once.
And then we're going to do
some playing of games.
Consider the problem CAR of
CONS of, say, 35 and 47.
Well, what is that?
It is the result of taking car
of the result of substituting
35 and 47 for X and Y
in the body of this.
Well, that's easy enough.
That's CAR of the result of
substituting into lambda of M,
M of 35 and 47.
Well, what this is, is the
result of substituting this
object for X in the
body of that.
So that's just lambda of M--
that's substituted, because
this object is being
substituted for X, which is
the beginning of a list,
lambda of M--
M of 35 and 47, applied to that
procedure of A and D,
which gives me A. Well, that's
the result of substituting
this for M here.
So that's the same thing
as lambda of A, D, A,
applied to 35 and 47.
Oh, well that's 35.
That's substituting 35 for A
and for 47 for D in A. So I
don't need any data at all,
not even numbers.
This is Alonso Church's hack.
Well, now we're going to do
something nasty to him.
Being a logician, he
wouldn't like this.
But as programmers, let's
look at the overhead.
And here we go.
I'm going to change the
definition of CONS.
It's almost the same as Alonzo
Church's, but not quite.
What do we have here?
The CONS of two arguments, X
and Y, is going to be that
procedure of one argument M,
which supplies M to X and Y as
before, but also to two
permissions, the permission to
set X to N and the permission
to set Y to N, given that I
have an N.
So besides the things that
I had here in Church's
definition, what I have is
that the thing that CONS
returns will apply its argument
to not just the
values of the X and Y that the
CONS is made of, but also
permissions to set X and
Y to new values.
Now, of course, just
as before, CAR
is exactly the same.
The CAR of X is nothing more
than applying X, as in
Church's definition, to a
procedure, in this case, of
four arguments, which selects
out the first one.
And just as we did before, that
will be the value of X
that was contained in the
procedure which is the result
of evaluating this lambda
expression in the environment
where X and Y are defined
over here.
That's the value of CONS.
Now, however, the
exciting part.
CDR, of course, is the same.
The exciting part, set CAR and
set CDR. Well, they're nothing
very complicated anymore.
Set CAR of a CONS X to a new
value Y is nothing more than
applying that CONS, which is
the procedure of four--the
procedure of one argument which
applies its argument to
four things, to a procedure
which is of four arguments--
the value of X, the value of
Y, permission to set X, the
permission to set Y--
and using it--using that
permission to set
X to the new value.
And similarly, set-cdr
is the same thing.
So what you've just seen is that
I didn't introduce any
new primitives at all.
Whether or not I want to
implement it this way is a
matter of engineering.
And the answer is of course I
don't implement it this way
for reasons that have to
do with engineering.
However in principle, logically,
once I introduced
one assignment operator,
I've assigned--I've
introduced them all.
Are there any questions?
Yes, David.
AUDIENCE: I can follow you up
until you get--I can follow
all of that.
But when we bring in the
permissions, defining CONS in
terms of the lambda N, I don't
follow where N gets passed.
PROFESSOR: Oh, I'm sorry.
I'll show you.
Let's follow it.
Of course, we could do
it on the blackboard.
It's not so hard.
But it's also easy here.
Supposing I wish to set-cdr of
X to Y. See that right there.
set-cdr of X to Y. X is
presumably a CONS, a thing
resulting from evaluating
CONS.
Therefore X comes from a place
over here, that that X is of
the result of evaluating
this lambda expression.
Right?
That when I evaluated that
lambda expression, I evaluated
it in an environment
where the arguments
to CONS were defined.
That means that as free
variables in this lambda
expression, there is the--there
are in the frame,
which is the parent frame of
this lambda expression, the
procedure resulting from this
lambda expression, X and Y
have places.
And it's possible to set them.
I set them to an N, which
is the argument of the
permission.
The permission is a procedure
which is passed to M, which is
the argument that the CONS
object gets passed.
Now, let's go back here in the
set-cdr The CONS object, which
is the first argument
of set-cdr
gets passed an argument.
That--there's a procedure of
four things, indeed, because
that's the same thing as this M
over here, which is applied
to four objects.
The object over here, SD, is,
in fact, this permission.
When I use SD, I apply
it to Y, right there.
So that comes from this.
AUDIENCE: So what do you--
PROFESSOR: So to finish that,
the N that was here is the Y
which is here.
How's that?
AUDIENCE: Right, OK.
Now, when you do a set-cdr,
X is the value the
CDR is going to become.
PROFESSOR: The X over here.
I'm sorry, that's not true.
The X is--set-cdr has
two arguments--
The CONS I'm changing and the
value I'm changing it to.
So you have them backwards,
that's all.
Are there any other questions?
Well, thank you.
It's time for lunch.